hey folks yes we'll redo the last five
minutes where we were saying incredibly
important things to you but you weren't
hearing them because of technical
difficulties so let's first say welcome
to this first livestream of the Dark
Horse podcast i'm here with dr. heather
huiying i am brett weinstein let me do
what I did last time and say we are
we're both PhDs in biology but we're not
medical doctors so we're gonna be
talking about the evolutionary
implications of what we're going through
both biological and social but we're not
providing medical advice okay we I would
say there might be some medically
relevant things but if we offer to do
surgery on you you should politely
decline definitely not surgeons despite
having some life skills right oh yeah
considerable knife skills all right so
let's talk a little bit about why we're
here we obviously collectively are
facing some sort of crisis there's can
somebody you know can you reload the
page and see whether or not it fixes the
problem
apologies folks this is this is the
first time from the studio we've
recently moved the studio to our house
expecting for a number of reasons but
expecting to be stuck in place
sheltering in place for a while here in
Portland Oregon so this Brett just
finished putting up the cedar that you
see in the background last night around
midnight I think installed the cabinets
and the butcher block behind us sometime
yesterday the day before that's going so
fast I can't really read it some people
seem to think it's working fine now this
is fine let's try yes no looks like it's
an awful lot of people if you are having
trouble with the lag so we will this
will be up this will be up be on the
live stream and we'll be out as a Dark
Horse podcast as well okay let's let's
hope that this is working and I need to
project as always apparently and get
down to some content okay so I'm gonna
try to ignore all the comments about the
lag hopefully you can ignore the lag
what our plan to do here is to discuss
elements of this crisis and it seems
that there are two crises unfolding and
an interesting interaction between them
we have obviously a crisis related to
kovat 19 and its spread and all of the
measures designed to flatten the curve
then we also have a crisis unfolding as
people are recognizing that the society
that we live in is structured in a
potentially fragile way and the problem
is that these two crises interact rather
directly not only is the virus causing
the fragility to show in the system but
it robs us of many of the measures that
we would ordinarily potentially use to
let's say rescue ourselves from a
depression there are many kinds of
stimulus it just simply won't work if
you have people being told to stay away
from each other mister lot
things just simply can't do that I saw
some of you were asking in the responses
to our tweets about this for a
discussion of game B in light of what's
going on which Bret has talked about in
other context and to the fourth frontier
which is a concept that Brett innovated
and we've both been writing about in a
book that we are writing and this is
this is probably not the hour or so that
we'll be talking about that but we hope
to be back every every few days and so
we'll get to talking about that at some
point soon just just to clarify fourth
frontier is my attempt to bootstrap a
kind of game B project game B was a
collaborative effort amongst a number of
people including Jordan Green Hall and
Jim rut so anyway we can we can return
to that topic later at the moment what
this crisis is doing is it is revealing
some of the things that those of us who
gathered for game B were concerned about
the things that brought us together was
a recognition that our system simply was
both inviting crises and unable to deal
with them which we are now seeing in
living color and you know the problem at
the moment that this particular moment
March 24th is that increasing in urgency
and volume is the idea that you can save
grandma or you can save the Dow and this
is a really an abhorrent way of framing
the issue and we somehow have to both
combat the virus and not tank worldwide
economy on the way but but preserving
the fragile systems that have been
created in explicitly anti fragile ways
is not necessarily the route to do and
so the other thing to realize is that
this crisis or this pair of crises is it
is revealing a core element that has
been missing from our political dialogue
which is effectively that our system
cannot help but optimize for economic
efficiency on short timescales it's
simply what it is built to do
and essentially you've got a two-sided
coin economic efficiency on short tides
timescales is on one side of that coin
and fragility is the other side you will
produce fragility to the extent that you
optimize economic efficiency on short
timescales and so that's where we've
landed and if there is a silver lining
here it is that if we come through this
crisis okay maybe we can learn the
lesson that it has to teach us about
what we've been doing wrong and
restructure so this can't happen again
it actually reminds me of something that
one of our graduate school professors
once said to us he was he was watching
squirrels berry nuts and sort of laughed
at them and suggested that squirrels are
dumb they're stupid because they berry
so many more nuts than they ever dig up
in a normal year it was the acorns
actually and of course this is this is
wrong and it is exactly the sort of
short-sighted thinking that is causing
us to panic right now that squirrels
berry acorns for the worst year that
they might encounter and those that
don't will benefit short-term and will
then probably parasitize those who don't
berry enough for the ten year winter the
hundred year winter the thousand year
pandemic whatever it is
so did we in fact either individually or
by city or by nation state or globally
berry enough acorns to deal with this we
certainly hope so and maybe we can learn
enough from what's going on right now to
both survive the pandemic and the
economic fallout all right so we had
well so we were I apologize I can't
remember what we said before when we
thought we were streaming and and since
we've been streaming we had wanted to
talk about some of the underlying
biology and how to interpret some of the
advice that's coming out in real time
from the media and the government with
an evolutionary lens so you can make
decisions for yourself and also some of
the societal impacts both of which are
evolutionary so maybe we want to start
with some of the biology let's start
with some of the biology let me just
pause here hey Zach if you were to
switch to the other audio source on the
camera would they sync okay fair enough
so zach is our 15 year old son who was
also our tech support okay so we were
going to talk about the biology and you
have a number of things that you've got
on the list of biological factors maybe
I would say something overarching first
the virus is not trying to kill you
that's going to sound odd it sort of
seems like viruses are built to do such
things and that that that's why we have
such a big problem but it is important
if you're going to think about things
like viruses to realize that they are
optimized to do exactly the same thing
that the rest of us are evolutionarily
speaking and while in school you may
have learned that Fitness is the same
thing as reproduction this is not the
correct way to think about it
creatures all of them are trying to get
into the future and they are trying to
get as deeply into the future as they
can this is true even though a virus
isn't technically a creature I actually
would differ a little bit on this point
I don't want to get stuck here but I
think when somebody says you know I
drove to the market the fact that they
had to use a car to do it does not mean
that they didn't actually drive to the
market and so anyway viruses are a very
interesting evolutionary phenomenon they
may indeed be genes that have escaped
from the kinds of creatures that they
parasitize and then they periodically I
mean a virus is just a an informational
molecule either DNA or RNA wrapped in a
coat that does some work to get it in
into a cell but basically that code
either integrates into the genome or
reverse transcribes and then integrates
into the genome and it instructs the
genome the distinction being if it
reversed transcribes it's called a
retrovirus and if it and if it codes
under the genome directly I don't think
I'm using the right language it's just
called a virus among which there are
many kinds of viruses including for
instance corona viruses so these codes
find their way into the genome and then
they hijack the cell for their own
purposes and their own purposes are they
create more virus in a form that it can
infect more creatures and this this
process frees them from a lot of the
constraints of something like a
bacterium would have if it was on this
mission because basically they've shed
all of the machinery necessary for life
and then they borrow it wherever they go
but if I can return to this point about
the virus is not trying to kill you
viruses like other creatures or parts of
creatures are trying to get as deeply
into the future as they can get what
what creatures do we see we see the ones
that have gotten this far into the
future so getting into the future is a
complex puzzle reproduction is one part
of that puzzle but it is not the only
part you can reproduce a lot and fail to
get into the future so we we could
understand that best by understanding
global collapse such that even though an
individual's still survived there was no
chance of them persisting into the
future beyond 20 years or so with all of
the supply chains and systems that were
dependent upon gone
we are not parasites by the usual
definition of the word but viruses
require a host I think I it must be that
all known viruses although neither of us
are biologists require a host to to be
active and so a virus that kills its
host and has no way of transmitting to a
new host is a failure as a virus and no
virus just like know anything wants to
be a failure in this regard and you know
we're using watts and such in this sort
of evolutionary shorthand there's of
course no consciousness ascribed to
viruses but a virus that kills its host
and is then stuck in that host to die as
well has has not succeeded in its viral
mission it behaves as if it wants is
basically when we say
that a creature wants that's what they
mean it behaves as if it wants so the
other thing to say though is the virus
doesn't even want to make you sick
ideally a virus would make you minimally
sick so that you did an effective job of
spreading it to the extent that you are
you know comatose somewhere you're not
interacting with other people so there
are parasites that actually do want to
knock you flat so malaria for example or
yellow fever are transmitted by a
mosquito that has much more access to
you if you're unable to swat them away
but a virus I would say that even with
the malaria and you know no one came
here to hear about malaria I'm sure but
there are four different species of
malaria right there's four different
Plasmodium species more than that but
there are four different malarial
Plasmodium species two of which are very
common one of which tends to leave you
walking around and hides in your liver
and comes back out and then your
infectious again it's vivax and then one
felt suprem tends to go to your brain
and kill you and that's called cerebral
malaria so even within you know a genus
of a totally different parasite of
Plasmodium that is that cause of malaria
there are wildly different strategies
but even even the the vivax the one that
leaves you walking around at the point
that it's most transmissible you're not
walking around so it it comes in waves
so it recurs and it'll knock you flat
leaves you vulnerable to mosquitos and
be transmitted but something like corona
virus or the flu have an interest in you
being functional enough that you spread
them around now this is why I raise this
point not only is this virus not
interested in making you sick it can't
help but make you sick but there is a
tendency over time for viruses to evolve
in the direction of being less
troublesome as indeed we've seen with
many of the other known corona viruses
which cause the common cold
they tend to be irritations in daily
life rather than causing what
Sarris co2 is causing now in the case of
this virus it has just met
humans presumably for the first time now
I believe that there is still debate
about what creature this emerged from
Pangolin is a possibility baddest funny
is a stronger possibility and really by
whatever mechanism even if somebody was
playing with this virus in a lab and it
escaped but they had ultimately gotten
it from bats this has implications and I
don't know so by this again by this has
implications what you mean is there is
no history shared between humans and
this virus that is that is that that
this you're talking well I mean I mean
something more than that
I very much want to know what creature
this came from even bat isn't good
enough bats are not interchangeable now
probably if this came from a bat it came
from a rhino low fat bat which would be
a gleaming insectivore an old-world
gleaning insectivore and probably cave
roosting now the reason that that
matters is if you think about it the
virus has to get spread in the creature
that it is native to now if you're a bat
and you're a gleaning insectivore you're
not encountering a lot of other gleaning
insectivores cleaning means you're
picking large insects off of plants and
things as opposed to hulking where
you're catching stuff in midair if
you're a gleaning insectivore then you
are not running into other bats you
don't have close contact with them while
you're out for it they don't call any
wrist no you do have close contact with
them when you're asleep during the day
and so the question is if this virus
came from a bat and was transported into
humans by some mechanism either a wet
market or a laboratory then does that
predict anything about the way in which
it is transmitted between humans in
other words does it regard night as the
time to be transmitted because bats are
active during the night and we are
active during the day and it registers
activity does it have some other well it
would be the opposite
if your story about the bats is true if
it's if it's simply based on photo
period no no this is my point it could
be that it's registering information
about what time of day it is it could
also be the bats have a signal this is
the active nozzle because we have the
opposite circadian rhythm is that right
exactly and so we know that this virus
is highly transmissible inside the home
part of the reason may be that our
dormancy takes place inside the home and
that the signal is causing it to emerge
at those periods of time it may also be
transmissible by for example you know I
wonder about waterborne transmission I
know it's possible for it to live in
water but the caves in which these bats
would be likely to roost often have
water flowing through them that's what
tends to form these caves and so anyway
just as long as there are a couple of
good segues there but let's at least go
to how do how do we currently understand
this particular virus to be transmitted
with the understanding that everything
that we know about this virus is very
new and some of it is likely to end up
being wrong but what we think we know
now is yes as we all know it's
aerosolized coughs I can hang in the air
for a couple of hours which is kind of
alarming clearly it goes through fecal
contact so wash your hands and don't
lick buts basically oh and perhaps blood
too okay so that's that's a possible
amount of transmission as well and that
side of this there's so many new
articles here we can maybe post it in
the notes afterwards or if you want to
put it up Zak you can but it's the same
at all 20/20 but we don't need it it can
remain on surfaces for a long time
copper is historically understood to be
this remarkable antimicrobial so it only
sticks around on copper for four hours
of up to 24 hours on cardboard up to
nine days maybe on hard surfaces like
stainless steel and plastic so what does
that mean if we know those things about
transmission you know how should you
behave when you get a package at your
door or or you know what would you do
with your doorknob and
such well one thing that's true is that
saying that a virus could remain active
and therefore transmittable on stainless
door knob for nine days does not mean
that if there was virus on that doorknob
at the point that someone coughed on it
or touched it with active viral load on
their hands that there is just as much
risk at that moment as there is nine
days out there's going to be a decay
function associated with it and so yes
you could you could possibly get this
virus from touching some kinds of
surfaces over a week after they've been
contaminated but it's still less likely
the farther out it is yes at the moment
so again I want to focus in on this
point this virus just met us it's doing
a bang-up job of spreading we are
deploying countermeasures the job of the
virus from its perspective is to get
into the future to the extent that we
deploy a countermeasure that frustrates
it in its quest to get into the future
it is in search of some alternate
modality and so almost all of the
variation in these this particular virus
will be lost almost all of it is going
to be in strains that are dead ends
occasionally one will discover something
and at the moment I think it is fair to
say that kovat 19 uses airplanes the way
malaria music uses mosquitoes right two
airplanes are transmitting the thing
between populations and we've seen that
be highly effective and now we've seen
travel has been shut down a very wise
move but what will it do next and more
importantly is there something about the
way we deploy countermeasures that can
successfully Corral the virus
evolutionarily I don't see enough people
thinking about this class so the we here
means both at the individual level at
the population level let me just jump in
and correct I misspoke earlier I said
that it can be aerosolized and there's
actually no evidence that it aerosol
eise's but it is air in airborne
droplets that can apparently hang in the
air before up to a few hours so the
distinction being it will not blow off a
dry surface into the air but it's
certainly in the air right it's
certainly in the air and actually highly
likely mode of transmission are droplets
yeah so point isn't I mean there's so
many things to get to but maybe some you
know this this gets one place this gets
us to is some of the rumors and innuendo
that have spread one of which is since
let's see in February 5th the New York
Times said don't wear masks it's not
helpful
On February 29th the US Surgeon General
said don't wear masks and that's
patently insane right now so this is
Thank You Zack this is the New York
Times for Bri v and then the you know
three weeks later and of course time
means everything in this in this crisis
the Surgeon General the US Surgeon
General says don't wear masks clearly in
part what they were doing if if they
knew what they were doing at all was
prioritizing Public Health over
individuals and thus understanding that
we had a perhaps global but certainly
national lack of supply of personal
protective gear they were trying to get
people from stockpiling masks but it is
it's gross negligence frankly to have
advised people for this long that masks
would do no good so you know Bret
tweeted out a couple days ago and it's
no now wearing and is tended to be
wearing a bandanna you know can is it
possible that's actually not effective
in any way from blocking the inhalation
of droplets into the nose or mouth of
course it's going to be effective will
it be as effective as an n95 or an 99 or
a 99 mask probably not well it depends
it could be more effective for you I've
taken a couple census because so
actually I'd like to go through this in
detail but the band
Anna functions right I'll tell you a
little bit about my sort of method of
using it but the fact is I actually do
wear it and I wear it when I go out and
a medical mask I might considered
wearing that too if I even had them but
the fact is this is just something that
I can deploy and I know I know how to
wear it you know in a way that it will
of course catch droplets I don't know if
you've compared them head to head in a
controlled test whether it would be as
effective as a mask maybe not but my
guess would be as in all complex
phenomena there's going to be
diminishing returns here and this is
going to be highly effective even if not
quite as effective and certainly if you
don't have masks as most people don't
its countermeasure worth deploying
absolutely anything else to say about
masks well let me let me give a sense of
how I've been managing this I've been
doing a lot of stuff out in the world
Heather and I moved to Portland recently
we were pretty well prepared when we
lived in Olympia for you know some
systems the breakdown of systems but
when we moved we lost a lot of the stuff
that we had been accumulating and so
anyway as this crisis has unfolded it
has been necessary for us to bootstrap
some sort of mechanism for continuing to
to be here you know in light of various
different crises if the light stays on
and the water stays on the gas stays on
it's one level of crisis if those things
were to fail it's very different but in
any case I've had a lot of reason that I
felt I had to go out into the world also
Zac our son and I had to rescue all the
materials for the Dark Horse podcast to
bring them back here so we spent four
late nights dismantling the studio and
bringing all the the elements here and
that required going into a space where
people were working and so well but you
mean you to be fair you were there
between about 10:00 and 2:00 in the
morning
each of four consecutive nights do you
specifically chose a moment when it
would maybe easier to to break down the
studio and to move it into the
truck and also when there would be very
likely no people around right but my
assumption is that the the space might
well be compromised absolutely so here's
what I want to get to when we're home
our assumption is that it's it's not
that they're going to be zero viral
particles here there are places we can
talk about where viral particles might
get through the door they're very
unlikely to infect us I'm talking about
our house and I think that this is
actually something that everybody needs
to seek to do that if you think about
the the cognitive load of some noise in
the background if there's a air
conditioner running you don't even know
that you're hearing it but as soon as it
goes off you feel the sense of relief
like oh my goodness because you're
spending all of this processing power
just getting rid of the noise of the air
conditioner the viruses like that you
just feel jeopardy all the time to the
extent that you can't sit down anywhere
and be sure that the surface is clean
you're constantly on alert and this is
really stressful which actually
ironically makes you more vulnerable so
figuring out how to get your house or
your apartment or wherever it is that
you're staying safe enough that you can
actually relax there is probably a
health issue and an important one so
what we've been doing is when I get up
in the morning I take a bandana and I
ordered 25 of them from Amazon weeks ago
knowing where we were and where we were
headed
and and weeks ago many many weeks ago it
was already impossible to buy masks of
any sort locally even just a handful so
when I get up I take a bandana and I put
it on even though I'm in the house and I
know it's safe here but I just want it
on so I don't have to go looking for it
you don't you don't walk around that
don't walk around the house I just put
up to fit it I tie it on like this so
I'm sure I've got the right fit and then
I just pull it down around my neck if
somebody comes to the door now
admittedly even UPS doesn't stick around
the door any longer
so I haven't in practice had a lot of
encounters with people but even if
somebody were to come to the door it's
right there and I don't have to think
about you know going to get it and
actually with there were some workmen
here and I did use it with them
but if I go to get some supplies or
something I'll Drive with it down then
I'll pull it up before I go into some
place and I'll put on these safety
glasses that have my reading
prescription underneath now these also
aren't going to be a hundred percent
effective but they do have some coverage
from the sides and the idea here is that
any droplet I encounter if I walk
through something a cloud that somebody
has coughed out could it get in my eye
sure is it likely - no because it has a
very complex path to get past my glasses
so I'll walk around like this I actually
have some cloth gloves I forgot to bring
them here but I have some cloth gloves
that I have multiple sets of I got them
very cheap at a hardware store now
they're not protective it's not like a
nitrile glove but it does mean if I
touch things that whatever gets on them
gets on them and then I can take them
off and as soon as I get back to the
vehicle I sanitize my hands before I
start touching the steering wheel and
all that and then I you know pull this
down and anyways you're done being out
for the day as soon as you're done being
out for the day you launder everything
yeah as I walk through the door I drop
my clothes in the laundry room and I go
take a shower and this serves two
important functions one if I've
encountered virus if it's in my hair
because I walked through a cloud of it
and didn't know this gets me back to
baseline where I can again not infect me
or my family and it means that I can
again feel that here I'm safe right and
that's an it's just an important factor
and you know if I've only been briefly
out and I don't feel like my clothes are
compromised and I'm working I'm not
touching things other people are going
to touch if I left my clothes on I would
still shower before I went to bed all
right so bed is a place I'm absolutely
not going to
you know drop some virus under the
pillow and get it into my eye or into
heather's I so anyway it's a it's a
method for both preventing infection and
it won't be a hundred percent effective
but I bet it's highly effective and also
for just creating a zone of
psychological safety where we spend most
of our time yeah good more to saying on
masks no I think we're good I think you
know there's there's a lot else a lot
too so you know on the on the subject of
rumors in a new window recently this is
you know putting a hair dryer up your
nose is not gonna cure coronavirus I
think the Florida Health official who
advised that has apologized since but
just in case you were wondering no
that's more likely to kill you probably
and all chloroquine is not the same so
do not do not imagine that if you hear a
report that suggests that the
chloroquine which is and I guess it's
hydrochloric one as well which is an
anti malarial prophylaxis it works
against five acts but feltzer prime to
go back to that and I guess it's used
for lupus rheumatoid arthritis as well
that drug which is already used in
humans is not it may be useful against
kovat 19 maybe in combination with
zithromax Arthur Ison as it's sometimes
called maybe in combination with
something else but just because you find
what does it clerk and phosphate on your
aquarium cleaner does not mean that you
should take that a couple of people one
person died one person is in critical
care from that so yeah am i right
zipper max does not have any activity
against the virus as far as we know but
the pneumonias that often travel with it
are liable to be actually I don't know I
don't know if it's the cocktail of
Zithromax and some form of chloroquine
that is thought to be effective or not
I'm not sure about that I think it's I
think the the that their axes is
strictly about the
than you yeah well so it's a widespread
antibiotic that is used specifically for
respiratory infections so it could be
yeah maybe we should talk about tests
yeah and and and people being
symptomatic and not symptomatic and
maybe go into before we go a society go
into the personal story sure I think I
think that may be the right the right
segue okay so an article in The
Financial Times which is now pay wold
so we can't show it to you suggested I
think it's today that half of Brits may
already be infected if true that's
actually really good news right that
means that the case fatality rate is
it's still being reported is way higher
than it actually is it does not mean
that this isn't that we that we don't
need to be in quarantine until we have
widespread testing so that we can know
but that if true it's great but how do
we know if it's true and I'm so glad
that the explanation is what you said
because I thought when you said it was
really good news that you meant finally
we've got the Brits right where we want
yes I'm still holding a grudge all these
hundreds of years later I hope that my
people were here then but right okay so
once infected even if you were
asymptomatic when you were infected and
it's clear that one of this viruses
strategies and again we're using
strategy as this is this known term that
does not imply any consciousness but
it's simply effective evolutionarily one
of the viruses strategies is to spread
through asymptomatic carriers so it
seems that likely everyone whether or
not you become symptomatic or not who
ends up infected with us has some period
of time before they are symptomatic
during which they can transmit it so
everyone who ends up with this thing
appears to be an asymptomatic carrier at
some point and those people who get sick
can then and can then think about where
they where they were and perhaps contact
those people but those people who never
got sick in the absent of widespread
antibody testing technically known as
serology testing we'll never know and
this you know if it's true
half of Great Britain is already
infected this is probably right that
it's just been spreading far well we
know it's spreading fast but it was
spreading far earlier and more easily
than we had any idea of so once infected
if if you recover as the vast majority
of people do although some percentage of
people who recover have will almost
certainly have long-term lung and
respiratory issues you are almost
certainly immune
now there's one report coming out of the
Taiwan Times Zack do you have that up
that was tweeted at me yesterday and I
can't find any other evidence of this
there's one report coming out the Taiwan
Times sometime in February I think or
maybe it was January suggesting that
repeated infections actually looked to
be more at more risk of being fatal but
these were initial infections that were
very bad and something it's unclear from
the report if it's the drugs that those
people were already on or the drugs that
they were being given to treat the
infection caused heart damage which then
meant that a second infection caused an
immune response basically the antibodies
themselves were working against the body
now this would be alarming and
horrifying if true for all sorts of
reasons and it would be a match for what
we think is going on with dengue which
is a like malaria another trop mostly
tropical always malaria always mosquito
vector disease so you can I think you
can take that town Zack sorry I got
distracted by the picture of the corona
virus so it Denton dengue it has been
known for some time that if you get
infected once you tend to be okay and if
you get it a second time it can it can
be fatal
and it seems that at low and maybe even
intermediate antibody loads antibodies
being the thing that your body produces
they can then recognize future
incidences of running into the pathogen
in this case of virus not in the case of
dengue it's not a virus but in in the
future at low and intermediate antibody
the inflammation that the antibody
response can actually cause can cause
something like respiratory distress that
can kill you
so if this is true it's super alarming
we don't see a lot of evidence that this
is true but that's something to to
consider that said all the other
evidence that I've seen suggests that if
you've had it
asymptomatic or not you now have
immunity at least for a spell so for a
spell as likely to mean immune to the
version of the virus that you've already
encountered because your immune system
recognizes it so quickly that you you
you don't get sick a second time one
correction there are two things that the
body produces that will recognize a
pathogen on reinfection one of them is
antibodies the other one is the
receptors on the t-cells but neither
here nor there really okay so oh so I
guess there are there are two types of
tests that we need to be widespread
widespread easily available cheap and
and quick turnaround so what we know in
the US and it seems like almost
everywhere in the world with some
important exceptions like tiny countries
like Iceland there are not enough tests
where the CDC is calling molecular
verses serology tests I find this
language confusing because it's all
molecular tests but the so-called
molecular tests are testing for active
infection so we need a lot more testing
for anyone presenting with symptoms or
for instance we just ran into yesterday
that apparently in nas mia loss of the
sense of smell in the absence of other
symptoms seems to be associated with
being a so-called asymptomatic carrier
of this thing so if you've experienced
the loss of smell or a partial loss of
the sense of taste which is of course
largely smell it could be that you are
carrying this thing we need tests to
test for active infection to allow those
people who have it to be treated I think
you should say that more strongly if in
this context you had a son sudden
unexplained loss
of the sense of smell it is highly
likely that you are infected and
therefore you should take extreme
measures not to pass it on and to ensure
that you do what's necessary to recover
so anyway you should behave accordingly
if you've got some other reason to have
lost your sense of smell different and
different analysis but were you to lose
it it would be a very strong indication
absolutely so those are the so-called
molecular tests and they're the tests
that we're hearing almost exclusively
about but what we also need is
widespread abundant easy cheap or free
serology testing which I prefer to call
antibody testing because antibody is a
word that most people have heard of
serology isn't so an antibody tests test
for whether or not your body has already
created an immune response to the virus
which would indicate that it's been
exposed that you have had it whether or
not you had symptoms and that if we're
right about those who have had it aren't
now immune for a spell you are now
immune now imagine if if this
epidemiological report reported in the
financial times is right and and what
was it 50 percent of yeah 50 percent of
people in Great Britain have already had
it how useful would it be to know if you
are in that 50 percent or not and you
you can be put back to work right away
we can get we can get economies running
by knowing whether or not people have
had it or not so that actually means
that Brits have us right where they want
us yeah that's right this is actually
probably this is the Brits you heard it
here first and last okay so the serology
testing antibody testing is also
potentially quite useful there's a
technique being pushed through and a
Johns Hopkins now being pushed through
regulations to pull plasma from people
who test positive for the antibodies
which can then be used in only a couple
of patients so it wouldn't you couldn't
use the plasma of one person who has had
and recovered from Kovan 19 and used it
to treat hundreds of patients but you
know about 1 to 2 ratio you could use it
to at least potentially confer
partial or temporary immunity to
healthcare workers or potentially to
boost response in the very sick so this
would be akin to the use of gamma
globulin in malarial context yeah so
these are antibodies to a particular
antigen yeah so did you say the serology
test has the advantage of being able to
tell you that you were exposed even if
you're no longer sick if you've defeated
the virus internally it will still
register a positive which is both good
and bad because and in fact it will not
register a positive for some number of
days after you've been infected so your
antibody load climbs I think it was
something like 14 days after you were at
your sickest if you were symptomatic and
so the serology tests are actually more
accurate a week or two out which makes
perfect sense because the reason that
you get sick in the first place is that
your immune system doesn't know the
formulas and Counting and encountering a
novel phenomenon and it takes time for
it to figure out molecular ly what that
phenomenon looks like and so if you test
for the antibodies to the virus and your
system has never seen that virus it's
going to take you know days to a week
for for the the test to register or
positive because you just simply don't
have any buddies yet that are specific
enough exactly let me just be clear also
that these Mallick the so called
molecular tests which test for active
infection and the antibody tests also
known as the serology test which tests
for prior exposure and yourself having
created an immune response within your
body molecular tests antibody tests
actually will not work at the same
moment in infection so there are some
number of people on the planet right now
who have not been exposed who will who
would test negative for either of these
things there's some number people who
have active infection right now and
would test positive for molecular tests
but not yet positive for serology tests
and then there are probably far more
people actually who have been exposed
who have recovered many of whom may not
even have known they were sick
who would test positive for an antibody
test a serology tests but serology tests
are not being done yet we don't have one
number I saw suggested five or six weeks
yet before their widespread
they they are likely the solution to
both the economic and the health crisis
and they're not the complete solution
but they are a big part of the solution
so they're a key piece so let me just
say that I you know I'm not able to see
the whole stream as it's going by of
course but when you hear numbers like
well you know Seattle tested or New York
tested and ninety percent of the people
they tested came back negative that does
not mean that those ninety percent of
people that they tested have not been
exposed and have never had it that what
that means is that they aren't currently
infected with with this coronavirus so I
saw somebody made the right distinction
in the chat the way to refer to it and
probably how we should refer to it with
each other is antigen versus antibody
right let's go you're testing for the
antibody you're testing your the fact of
your immune system having understood
wedeck's up against the antigen being
pathogen antibody being our response to
pathogen our molecular signatures that
are particular to the path again so your
own cells will have these viral markers
on them as a result of being infected
yeah all right so we talked about our
yeah I guess so we definitely want to
get to talking about society what how
much time are we in at this point Zack
yeah okay well well we will we will be
we're gonna continue a bit here but we
will be back again in a few days as well
so boy I haven't practiced how I tell
this story I'm gonna be as brief as
possible and if people want more details
maybe actually if can I introduce her
okay so a few days ago no maybe a week
ago that's a week ago at this point um
Heather came to me and said I have a
hypothesis for you um is it possible
that I already had kovat 19 she had been
quite sick with something we took to be
flu and at the time I said there's
almost no chance that you had it because
it was so rare in the u.s. at the time
that the chances of having encountered
somebody with it virtually ruled it out
that said there were other things about
what Heather had which then Zach our son
picked up that matched so well the set
of symptoms and the let's say the level
of sickness that both Heather and Zach
had was quite alarming in fact I thought
about taking Zach to the hospital at one
point he just sort of seemed to have
lost it was a joke at the time because
we thought he had the flu and would
certainly recover but he seemed to have
lost his will to live he was just
completely flattened so anyway yeah let
me let me walk through a little bit of
why I'm I've also checked my logic
against a couple of public health
friends and they agree that this is
almost certainly and I we can't know we
don't know because there is no antibody
testing available to us yet but I was in
LA where it seems that it probably was
present earlier than anyone is saying is
clear that we have been data has been
kept from us and we've probably actively
been lied to by many sources from the
beginning of this thing so I was in LA
between February 6th and 11th came back
that night started coughing I was
sitting on the couch with Breton or two
boys and commented that's a weird cough
why am i coughing so suddenly middle of
the night I'm coughing more and more and
I'm feeling wretched we are lucky enough
to be in a situation in our house where
we have a spare bed with a guest bed but
I just gotten home and I don't want to
wake but Brett up in the middle of the
night and say you need to you need to
switch bedrooms
so Brett spent a night sleeping next to
me when I was coughing by the time I got
up I said well I'm I'm really really
sick and and I cancelled a couple of
plans that I had for the day and I was
just flattened totally flattened for the
day coughing the only thing that was
that seemed likely to do any good for me
was to sit in a hot bath which I did for
hours
and and otherwise I was just lying in
bed Brett went to dinner with the people
we'd had plans with that evening having
since you moved out of the bedroom and
effectively we're lucky to be able to
quarantine each of us if we need to
within the house so actually I want to
return to this maybe yeah next time but
this has been policy in our house where
we treat infectious disease very
seriously because just the for a number
of reasons but anyway when somebody's
sick one of us is sick we separate so we
don't sleep next to each other and but
you spend a night sleeping next to me
and because Brett was out that night i
roused myself that are barely and sat
with our two boys as they ate dinner and
I took my temperature at that point and
it was 102 I don't know okay yeah I
really I really am sick I thought I
broke the fever that night it certainly
felt like it but when I took my
temperature again 24 hours later it was
still 102
I mean while the coughing can go on for
half an hour at a time
the only thing that seems to relieve the
pain and the pressure at all is is hot
steamed lemon honey tea which you made
for me and baths and showers
no no throat involvement which is rare
for me when I get sick no just um ik no
sneezing coughing fever and I'm you know
I'm an extremely healthy active you know
50 year old woman and female is somewhat
protective against this and also being
in good health with no underlying
conditions my age being really the only
thing that I know of that puts me at
some higher risk there's there's more to
that story and I'll say one more one
more detail here about my experience but
I also want to say that two days into me
being sick Zach gets sick he's 15 years
old he is an extraordinary health he has
no underlying conditions none of us are
on any pharmaceuticals and he's never
get sick and this boy was flattened and
he had a hundred four degree fever he's
coughing and Brett almost took him to
the hospital this is before we had any
thought of it being cope at night yeah
we don't have
any reports of hospitalizations for
people under 20 I think and here is this
incredibly healthy 15 year old who was
totally flattened by this thing for four
days so here's one other thing that I
think is relevant for people if they
think they might have this because I've
seen glimmerings anecdotal stuff
otherwise to this effect
I've still got with this file this is
like five weeks later that 96 hours
almost to the hour like four days
exactly after beginning to get sick on
the 15th I was in the shower and I had
the sort of step function improvement in
health like and I am not all the way
better but I feel like I'm gonna live
and I didn't ever think I was going to
die but I Wow
do I feel like okay I've just rounded
the corner and in a way that usually you
don't with sickness you feel like a
little better when you wake up maybe but
this really felt like a step function
and so that was the evening of Friday
the 15th no Saturday the 15th we had
postponed dinner plans with a friend a
former student who was in town in part
to see us the day before for the day
after in the 16th and I woke up on the
16th just feeling so much better okay
good we can go see debt and you know I
struck the bed like okay you know maybe
maybe we're gonna give it a couple more
days before Brecon come back in but
feeling much better let's get these news
what are you sheets off here Zack was by
now doing a little bit better he was
still sick but we felt okay to leave him
home alone while Brett and I and our
younger son went to have dinner with our
friend at dinner I started coughing so
furiously that I had to leave the
restaurant I stood outside coughing for
ten minutes and this happened twice more
and I thought I what what the hell is
this this is unlike anything else I've
ever experienced and it was hard to walk
back to the car and by the time we got
home I had stripped the bed but the
laundry hadn't been ready so I hadn't
made the bed Brett and I were trying to
make the bed and I I couldn't I actually
could not stand up I I fell to my knees
and then I had to
and I could not do it and I don't know
if it was that night or the next night
so Brett did not sleep nice to me that
night of course
so Brett finished making the bed and it
was either in the middle of that night
or the next night that I woke up
asphyxiating like for the only time
during this really actually feeling like
I was going to die and like I was I was
unable to get breath the alarming thing
about this and it only happened once and
I obviously did not die but the alarming
thing to me about this is the having
felt so much better that I went out into
the world that I thought I was over it
that I went out into the world and I
potentially exposed not just our friend
but a whole restaurant full of people
because I thought I was better and you
know as soon as I was coughing I
extricated myself again there was no
thought that this was Co vat19 we had
heard of Kovac 19 at this point when we
emerged from the Amazon there was
thought to be one case in Ecuador and so
it made the the news in Ecuador and that
was our first encounter with the whole
concept yeah this is late January we'd
been in the Amazon and Internet free
field station for a couple of weeks and
we came out we heard about it and we
we've been tracking it since then and it
really was a week ago
that I put together you know what at
some level given how much misinformation
disinformation there is out there about
what this is where it's been when it's
been and how bad it's been why do why is
the only thing that isn't a match for
what I've experienced and what this is
is the timing but la in early
mid-february could could well have been
a source well and you know within two
days of you're having floated this idea
that maybe it was Cove in 19 and my
having dismissed it evidence emerged
though you didn't dismiss it well no I
dismissed it on the basis that it was so
unlikely you would have contracted it
that then two days later evidence
emerged that in fact there were a great
many more cases in January then we had
understood and suddenly everything fell
into place so we don't know that you had
it but it does seem
likely and then that raises a question
about me and our other son
exactly Toby yes I felt I have
historically been pretty susceptible to
respiratory illness and when you guys
got sick I felt certain that I was going
to get it and I was extremely careful
but I it struck me as very unlikely that
I would be able to be careful enough in
the same house as the two of you as sick
as you were and not get it and we
actually had a little celebration at the
point that we were 14 days from our
first exposure from know from your both
being recovered because at that point we
were pretty sure somehow Toby and I had
avoided it now at this point let's say
it was Kovac 19 we don't know whether
Toby and I had it and were asymptomatic
and going out into the world right I
have type O+ blood and type O blood is
protective so it's possible I didn't get
it because my blood is protective it's
possible I had it and was asymptomatic
but this is a hold on let's just flag
that that type O blood there's eight
there's a paper out sac I don't know if
you want to put it up you don't have to
it's the sow at all 2020 paper that
suggests that the and this was out of
China this is in Chinese hospitals I
think that people with a b and b blood
types had about the expected risk of
susceptibility to cope at 19 people with
type O blood had lower than expected
risk of people with type A blood has
slightly higher and it's those those are
statistically significant results but
they aren't extreme it's not the people
with type O blood never get it or the
people with type A blood always get it
this is somewhat protective so to go
back to your earlier point about testing
we are now stuck in a situation I mean
you can see we think that there's a
decent chance that everybody in our
family has had the
already which would render us largely
protected you can see how careful were
being anyway though I mean the thing is
we're taking no chances we're taking
this very seriously even though we now
are doing so with the thought that maybe
even if we do encounter it we won't come
down with it
but how useful would it be to know that
we were passed kovat 19 to the extent
that there is concern out there and
there's this mean which I haven't
encountered yet I've been too busy to be
spending any time doing even the due
diligence I should be doing online but
to the extent that people are now
recognizing a trade-off between you know
protecting the elderly and protecting
the economy for example how important
might it be to know who it is who has
passed this and can actually be helpful
and you know intervene where others
would fear to tread
that's our so if if it is if it has been
spreading through the US and the other
weird countries for several months
there are a lot of us who have it and
didn't know and could be usefully
contributing to the economy and to our
own individual success and I mean let's
say you know one of our parents got sick
right if our parents got sick we could
not afford to go into their space to
take care of them or we would have to
think very carefully about how to do it
because we would be putting other people
at risk should we contract it you know
so it's a very tough puzzle but if we
know that we've had it then it's the
obvious thing to do so anyway there are
a lot of predicaments that could be
resolved if we simply knew where in the
progression of this you are are you
vulnerable are you passed it and so
anyway the complete failure of our
governmental apparatus to deliver us
both quality information and tests
capable of telling us in which category
we individually are
is inexcusable those are the things that
allow you to navigate this intelligently
and and it's just unacceptable that we
have no that is we need we need data we
need we need to know to to the degree
possible where all of us stand with
regard to past infection
obviously current infection but all all
of the discussions about testing almost
in the media and from the government are
about tests that are only looking at
current infection and you can't use
those to restart the economy the people
who are so sick that they are now being
tested since they're in such short
supply are not going to be the ones
going back to work anytime soon you have
a whole lot of people and we have no
idea how many we have no idea even what
order of magnitude number of people
there are who are now almost certainly
recovered were asymptomatic have
antibodies are immune at least for some
time and could be back at work that does
not mean that we can release quarantine
that we should not be sheltering in
place all of these things for now
because without the information
loosening up these strictures that we're
all living under now would be calamitous
alright other things you want to include
here are some more to say but maybe we
should say we'll be back in a couple
days what's up one hour now okay
unless I mean we could do let's do it
let's let's skip the society for now
let's go let's go back to there do you
want it do you want to do that now yeah
if society know so what should what
should individuals be doing now and
we'll talk a little bit more about the
societal impacts and such in a few days
couple few days yes we need to be
socially distancing and if if you can
when you're out be wearing masks be
wearing eye protection this sort of
thing but that does not mean staying in
your home and some number of people live
in conditions where they can't socially
distance and leave their home
and that is hard and I don't have the
answer to that but most most people do
not live in that situation if you can go
outside you should go outside having the
Sun on your face is healthy viruses
don't like Sun vitamin D is good for you
it's an antiviral itself being outside
especially if you can manage to be in
nature is going to be good for you if
the weather permits when you're inside
open windows get a cross-breeze it is
actually known and Zac you might put up
the Hobday 2019 paper thanks to Mike
Mars on Twitter for first alerting me to
this fresh air is actually understood to
be healing then we know this both from
lower rates of tuberculosis and hospital
rooms with OpenAL windows on more than
one wall and from SARS one which you
know this is SARS to what we're living
through right now from SARS one there
were I believe it's lower transmission
rates of SARS one in hospitals with
cross ventilation and specifically not
mechanical cross ventilation but natural
cross ventilation
so if especially if you're living with
people who aren't a hundred percent
careful but even if you are if you can
open windows when you're inside at least
some part of every day to get cross
ventilation get moving stay active get
plenty of sleep stay hydrated eat whole
real food including and this is the
thing that maybe you won't have heard
pursuing cravings so long as they're not
for you know Cheetos or ice cream but
pursuing cravings involve real food just
like we're advised to do when pregnant
that the body will tell you often what
it needs by saying I really want that
well the experience I had in the wake of
this thing that Zach and I had that may
or may not have been covered 19 I was
joking with Brett well you know now I
got scurvy I could not get enough citrus
and you know for a week or two
afterwards just ate you know eight or
ten tangerines and oranges a day so if
your body is saying I'm really crazy for
citrus right now go get yourself some
citrus and hopefully you have it in your
home already and if you have to go out
do a big shop and try to go out more
than once a week etc but if you have
cravings that involve real whole food
and especially if they aren't for things
is that you always want pay attention to
those there's a good chance that they're
for real yeah no so there's clearly a
psychological danger that shelter in
place is good epidemiological advice it
has many consequences most of us are not
you know cabin fever is a real thing and
it is going to compound the problem so
Heather is right you're the outdoors are
your friend if you can stay away from
other people I mean six feet isn't you
can certainly have a conversation with
somebody
Peter big ocean and I went bird-watching
the other day but it's a it's it's
definitely an important thing to
consider which is how are you going to
keep yourself feeling like you're not
just simply cooped up hiding from an
enemy outside your house in some ways
we've got tools that are at our disposal
that are extremely valuable I mean how
much more isolating would this be if you
know the internet resources were not
available to us and in fact I think
there's an argument to be made that our
ability to interact with each other over
the Internet
offers some relief here because there
are lots of things that we can use to
substitute for the kinds of interactions
that we would have in person outside of
this epidemic
so anyway consider what those might be
I'm thinking of starting something like
a campfire a virtual campfire where
people gather using some sort of
streaming service in order to just stay
in sync with other people and to
brainstorm ideas for what to think about
what we're facing but anyway there's
lots available to us just one more thing
we saw a number of questions that we
haven't addressed both certainly we
missed almost everything that stroll to
the stream here but that we saw on
Twitter
one question that I saw come up several
times was the status of the book that
we're writing so let me say that we we
turned in a first draft on March 8th
and it's due out in spring of next year
and it is a hunter-gatherers guide to
the 21st century and
this kind of thinking around you know
what to eat what to do how to be
including up to Society level stuff
which will begin to get to a little bit
in our next live stream yes and with any
luck if you order a copy it will come
with a bottle of isopropyl alcohol by
then hopefully there will not be a
shortage of isopropyl alcohol alright so
let us sign off here for this episode of
the Dark Horse podcast live and we will
address our technical issues and return
in a couple of days alright alright guys